Guide to the Julius Bernstein Papers WAG.116
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Julius Bernstein Papers
1920-1984
1950-1977
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Bernstein, Julius, 1919-
Walter P. Reuther Library
Bernstein, Arthur
Bernstein, Stanley
WAG.116
52 Linear Feet in 45 record cartons, 6 flat boxes, 5 oversize folders in shared boxes, and 1 oversize flat file folder.
Julius Bernstein (1919-1977) served for more than twenty-five years as a field representative of the Jewish Labor Committee based in Boston, but with responsibility for all of New England. A tireless advocate of civil rights, he served on the Massachusetts Advisory Committee of the U.S. Commission on Human Rights and was appointed as a labor representative to the Boston Housing Authority (which he later served as Chairman) in 1968. An active member of the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee and the Socialist Party, Bernstein was also a member or officer of the Workmen's Circle, the American Veterans Committee, the Massachusetts Civil Liberties Union and many community-based organizations. The collection includes correspondence, reports, flyers, photographs, and clippings reflecting the range of Bernstein's interests and political involvements. Also included are four banners, and a variety of pennants and insignia. Of note are rare materials documenting housing, school desegregation and other political struggles in Boston.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Julius Bernstein Papers were transferred to the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, New York University, from the Walter P. Reuther Library at Wayne State University, Detroit under an agreement with the Bernstein family in 1995. The transfer was facilitated by Julius Bernstein's brother Arthur and his elder son, Stanley. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1995.003 and 1995.014. The papers had originally been deposited at the Reuther Library in 1978; when the transfer to NYU occurred a substantial portion of Bernstein's books, pamphlets and periodicals remained at Wayne State.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Julius ("Julie") Bernstein (1919-1977) served for more than twenty-five years as a field representative of the Jewish Labor Committee based in Boston, but with responsibility for all of New England. A tireless advocate of civil rights, he served on the Massachusetts Advisory Committee of the U.S. Commission on Human Rights and was appointed as a labor representative to the Boston Housing Authority (of which he later became Chairman) in 1968. An active member of the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee and the Socialist Party, Bernstein was also a member or officer of the Workmen's Circle, the American Veterans Committee, the Massachusetts Civil Liberties Union and many community-based organizations.
Bernstein was born in New York City to Solomon ("Sam") and Rose Kimmel Bernstein. His father was born in a small town near Odessa in Russia, and his mother in Halicz in the Austro-Hungarian Empire; both came to the United States in their teens. He was trained in Orthodox Jewish observance, and though he soon abandoned religious commitment, he retained a passionate interest in traditional Jewish culture. The family moved to Boston, where his father was a partner in a used auto parts business and his mother worked in garment shops, during his primary school years. Julius attended Boston Latin School, Roxbury Memorial High School, and, during another brief sojourn in New York, graduated from James Monroe High School; in the Bronx. He later attended the Boston University School of Journalism for one year, while steadfastly resisting his father's efforts to interest him in a business or civil service career.
He was drafted by the U.S. Army in December 1941. In his son Stanley's words, "He prided himself on never rising above the rank of private first class, and for his G.I.'s disdain for officers." He was honorably discharged in 1945. He had married Bess Belle Luff in 1940, and the couple had two sons, Stanley, born in 1941, and Eugene Debs, born in 1943.
After holding a few short-term odd jobs, Julius Bernstein found his vocation in life when we he went to work, in 1948, at the Boston office of the Jewish Labor Committee at 27 School Street. He started as an assistant to the JLC's field representative for Boston, Rose Parker. When Parker relocated to Detroit Bernstein succeeded her. The JLC, whose mission was to act as a bridge between the labor movement and the organized Jewish community, had a national office in New York and field offices in major fifties across the country. Field office work was coordinated by JLC National Secretary Emanuel Muravchik and one of his chief assistants, Betty Kaye Taylor. Another JLC staffer who became a close friend and eventually relocated to Boston, where he did civil rights work, was Jacob Schlitt. Always a self-starter and something of a maverick within the JLC, Bernstein in the early years aimed to make the JLC-Boston the education arm of organized labor in New England on human rights issues. An annual Human Rights Awards Dinner, held throughout the 1960s and 70s, became the primary fund-raising vehicle for the JLC-Boston. He produced literature for display and distribution and conducted seminars at countless state, regional and local labor gatherings. A dynamo of activity, he soon branched out to become a key player in a long list of state and local organizations, on a host of related issues, from housing and education to police-community relations, immigrant rights and the campaign for Soviet Jewry. His School Street office became a hub of community and radical activism, especially in the strife-torn years of intense civil rights and anti-war struggle in the city. He became a court-appointed community mediator during the period of Louise Day Hicks's anti-school-busing campaign. Along the way Bernstein built strong connections to the varied ethnic, religious, labor, neighborhood and political constituencies of the city, while maintaining his personal ties to secular and progressive Jewish groups such as the Workmen's Circle and to the democratic socialist movement.
Beginning in the mid-1960s, Bernstein served as a member of the Massachusetts State Advisory Committee of the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights (also known as the Massachusetts Commission on Human Rights). The Advisory Committee was then chaired by Father (later Congressman) Robert F. Drinan; its work included path-breaking studies of segregation in housing, employment and public schools; investigations of civil rights violations; and involvement in the defense of Native American rights. An early supporter of "fair housing" measures, Bernstein was appointed in 1968 by Mayor Kevin White to a five-year term as a "labor representative" to the Boston Housing Authority. He went on to become Chairman of the Authority, in which capacity he became involved in the Doris Bunte Case, dispute in which Bernstein sought to defend the Authority against the Mayor's efforts to exercise political patronage and arbitrarily replace Mrs. Bunte. The case was finally decided in the Authority's favor by the Superior Court; Mrs. Bunte was reinstated and went on to serve under successive mayors until 1992. As a consequence of the case Bernstein was not reappointed to a second term.
Among the many organizations of which he was supporter, a member or an officer were Mothers for Welfare Rights, the A. Philip Randolph Institute, Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee, the Civil Liberties Union of Massachusetts, the Mattapan-Dorchester Jewish Committee, the Citizens Housing and Planning Association, the Civil Rights Committee of the Massachusetts State Labor Council, and the Ernie Pyle Chapter of the American Veterans Committee. He also amassed files on right-wing extremists and their organizations, in particular the Massachusetts-based John Birch Committee.
The Bernsteins' home in Jamaica Plan served as a welcoming social venue for his many political friends and allies, and was a way-station for visiting speakers and political notables of labor and the left. As Stanley Bernstein wrote, "Oftentimes, labor leaders and political and civil rights activists from other cities and foreign countries (including Norway, Austria, India, and Great Britain) stayed the night…. The guests included… Bayard Rustin, James Farmer, Joe Glazer, Don Slaiman, Michael Harrington and…Hugh Gaitskell." Harrington and Rustin, along with garment-union leaders Sol Chaiken and Jacob Sheinkman served as chairmen of a testimonial dinner honoring Bernstein in 1974.
Bernstein suffered from cardiac disease from an early age, and suffered a mild heart attack in his early fifties. He died of a massive heart attack at age 58 in November 1977 and is buried in the Workmen's Circle Cemetery in Peabody, MA.
Sources:
Stanley Bernstein, "Biographical Essay on Julius Bernstein," c.1992 (unpublished, copy in Bernstein accession file, Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, NYU).
Scope and Content Note
The Bernstein Papers reflect the full range of organizational connections and political contacts of a man whose interests ranged from right-wing extremism to Yiddish culture. In addition to the correspondence, reports, official analyses and privately funded studies of urban issues, flyers, clippings and notes documenting his own activity, he collected political ephemera and kept up a private correspondence with activists all over the country. His frankness and his tendency to embrace positions somewhat to the left of his socialist and labor contemporaries is well illustrated in his freewheeling (sometimes acerbic) correspondence with JLC staffers Emanuel Muravchik and Betty Kaye Taylor; in his long exchanges with Young People's Socialist League activists, especially on the Vietnam War; and in many letters he exchanged with his friend Bill Kelmsley, who kept him posted on the labor scene in upper New England.
Another friend, Jack Plunkett, writing a memorial tribute in the Yankee Radical (1980), produced a colorful picture of Bernstein's office at 27 School St.: "… a half-dozen four drawer file cabinets whose drawers stuck, almost bulging with files of organizations: the Massachusetts Committee on Discrimination in Housing, the American Veterans Committee, the Massachusetts Commission on Human Rights, the Workmen's Circle, Citizens Housing and Planning Association, the state Advisory Committee to the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, four years of minutes of meetings of the Boston Housing Authority, complaints of migrant workers, Socialist Party records from the 50's, two entire file cabinets of every right-wing organization that had cropped up in two decades and on and on. Piles of clippings and reports tower from every horizontal surface… on the wall, a dusty picture of Karl Marx, askew, and near it another of Eugene Debs… [and] a large sketch of Norman Thomas. Nearby a rickety wooden pigeon-hole file crammed with pamphlets, notes, books, balanced on a table littered with papers." Not every piece of paper survived to be transferred to the archives, but enough remains to reflect the main outlines of Bernstein's activism and enthusiasms.
As Plunkett noticed, in addition to archival materials Julius Bernstein accumulated a very large number of books, pamphlets and periodicals. Hundreds of serial titles, representing a wide range of organizations and subject-matter, were found in the collection. They included national, regional and local labor periodicals, publications of student and community groups in the Boston area, the underground and alternative press of the 1960s and 70s, journals devoted to progressive Jewish politics and culture, newsletters of the many organizations Bernstein supported or joined, civil rights, civil liberties and peace movement publications and a substantial cross-section of publications emanating from extreme right-wing groups.
Arrangement
Folders in Series I and II are arranged alphabetically. Series III has not been arranged by an archivist. The collection has three series, one of which has been divided into subseries:
Series I: Subject Files, 1920-1984
Series II: Non-Print Materials, 1940-1973
Subseries IIA: Photographs, 1947-1971
Subseries IIB: Artifacts and Ephemera, 1947-1973
Series III: Unprocessed Materials, 1938-1977
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into two series:
Missing Title
I, Subject Files, 1920-1984
II, Unprocessed Materials, 1938-1977
Separated Materials
Posters seperated from this collection during processing can be found in the Tamiment/Wagner Poster and Broadside Collection (GRAPHICS 002).
Labor unions |z Vermont.; Refuseniks.; Labor unions |z Maine.; Labor unions |z New Hampshire.; Jews |z Soviet Union |x Migrations |x Public opinion.; Labor unions |z Massachusetts.; Discrimination in housing.; Discrimination in employment |z Massachusetts.; Banners.; Scrapbooks.; Pennants.; Black-and-white photographs.; Fliers (printed matter); Posters.; Reports.; Minutes (administrative records); Boston (Mass.); Newsletters.; Boston (Mass.) |x Politics and government.; Clippings (information artifacts); Boston (Mass.) |x Race relations.; Civil rights |z Massachusetts |z Boston.; New England.; Correspondence.; Civil rights -- United States.; School integration |z Massachusetts |z Boston.; Young People's Socialist League; Taylor, Betty Kaye, -2011; Muravchik, Emanuel, d. 2007; Parker, Rose; Bunte, Doris; Bernstein, Julius, 1919-; United States Commission on Civil Rights; Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring; Jewish Community Council (Boston, Mass.); Massachusetts Commission against Discrimination; Boston Labor Committee to Combat Intolerance; Boston Housing Authority; John Birch Society; Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.); American Veterans Committee; Walter P. Reuther Library; Bernstein, Arthur; Bernstein, Stanley
- Series I: Subject Files, 1920-1984
  - A. Philip Randolph Institute, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A. Philip Randolph Institute, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Academic Freedom, 1952-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Action for Boston Community Development, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3a)
  - Affirmative Action, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Affirmative Action (Universities), 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Age Discrimination, 1955-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Alliance for Labor Action, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Am Chai, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Amalgamated Meat Cutters, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8a)
  - America First, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - American Arbitration Association, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - American Automobile Association, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - American Conservative Union, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - American Council of Christian Churches, 1954-1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - American Federation of Labor, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - American Federation of Labor - Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO), undated, 1954-1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - AFL-CIO: Department of Education, 1956-1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - AFL-CIO: Ethics, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - AFL-CIO: Foreign Policy, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - AFL-CIO: Housing, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 19a)
  - AFL-CIO: Merger, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - AFL-CIO: Rhode Island, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - American Federation of Musicians, 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - American Federation of Teachers Caucus on Desegregation, undated (Box 1, Folder 22a)
  - American Flag Committee, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - American Forum for Socialist Education, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - American Independent Party (George Wallace), undated, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - American Institute, 1955, 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - American Jewish Congress, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - American Jewish Historical Society, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - American Jewish League against Communism, undated, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - American Jewish Tercentenary, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - American Mercury, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - American National Party, 1962, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - American Nazi Party, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - American Republican Army, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - American Veterans Committee, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - American Veterans Committee, Jan 1948-Jun 1948 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - American Veterans Committee, Jul 1948-Dec 1948 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - American Veterans Committee, Jan 1955-May 1955 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - American Veterans Committee, Jun 1955-Dec 1955 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - American Veterans Committee, Jan 1956-Apr 1956 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - American Veterans Committee, May 1956-Aug 1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - American Veterans Committee, Sep 1956-Dec 1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - American Veterans Committee, Jan 1957-Mar 1957 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - American Veterans Committee, Apr 1957-Jun 1957 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - American Veterans Committee, Jul 1957-Dec 1957 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - American Veterans Committee, Jan 1958-Mar 1958 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - American Veterans Committee, Apr 1958-Jul 1958 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - American Veterans Committee, Aug 1958-Dec 1958 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - American Veterans Committee, Jan 1959-Apr 1959 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - American Veterans Committee, May 1959-Aug 1959 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - American Veterans Committee, Sep 1959-Dec 1959 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - American Veterans Committee, Jan 1960-Feb 1960 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - American Veterans Committee, Mar 1960-Dec 1960 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - American Veterans Committee: Civil Rights Conference, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - American Veterans Committee: Civil War Centennial, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - American Veterans Committee: Constitutions & By-Laws, 1946-1957 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - American Veterans Committee: Ernie Pyle Chapter - Newsletters, Jul 1946-Dec 1948 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - American Veterans Committee: Ernie Pyle Chapter - Newsletters, 1949-1960 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - American Veterans Committee: Massachusetts Veteran, 1947-1959 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - American Veterans Committee: National Chapter Newsletter, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Americans for Constitutional Action, 1961, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Angoff, Sam: Testimonial Dinner, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 4a)
  - Ansora, Michael, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 4b)
  - Anti-Semitism, 1948, 1960-1975 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Anti-Semitism: Dorchester, Mass., 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Anti-Semitism: In Witch Hunts, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Anti-Semitism: South America, 1962-1967 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Apprenticeship: Boston, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Apprenticeship Information Center, 1963-1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Arab Boycott, 1956-1961, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Arab Boycott, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Armed Forces: Discrimination, 1948-1968 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Assault on Equality Conference, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Association of American Physicians and Surgeons, 1960-1963, 1966, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Attorney Advertising (Bernstein Testimony), 1977 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Aware, Inc. (Faulk Case), 1962-1965 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Baldwin, James, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 17a)
  - Bay State Banner, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Bernstein, Julius: Testimonial Dinner, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18a)
  - Bernstein, Stanley, 1960-1974, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Bicentennial: Boston, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Birmingham, AL, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Black Panthers, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Black Power, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Black Students Work-In Committee, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Blacks and Jews, 1960-1965 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Blacks and Jews, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Blacks and Jews, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Blacks and Jews, 1969, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Blacks and Jews: Allston/Brighton, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Black Community in Boston, 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Black Extremists, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Black Family (Moynihan, etc.), 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Black Nationalists/Black Muslims, 1960-1968 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Blacklisting: Entertainment, 1956-1967 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Blacks and Labor, 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Blanshard, Paul, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Blum, Leon, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Bombings (Against Southern Jewry), Late 1950's (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Boston: African-American Community, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Boston Community Media Committee, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Boston Housing Authority, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Boston Housing Authority, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Boston Housing Authority, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Boston Housing Authority, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Boston Housing Authority, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Boston Housing Authority, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Boston Housing Authority, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Boston Housing Authority, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Boston Housing Authority, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Boston Housing Authority, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Boston Housing Authority, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Boston Housing Authority: Bernstein Compensation, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Boston Housing Authority: Bunte Case, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Boston Housing Authority: Bunte Case, Jan 15, 1971-Jan 22, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Boston Housing Authority: Bunte Case, Jul 8, 1971-Feb 14, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Boston Housing Authority: Bunte Case: Clippings, Mar 30, 1971-Jul 13, 1971 (Box 4A, Folder 1)
  - Boston Housing Authority: Bunte Case: Clippings, undated, Jul 14, 1971-Dec 16, 1972 (Box 4A, Folder 2)
  - Boston Housing Authority: Bylaws, 1969 (Box 4A, Folder 3)
  - Boston: Jewish Community, 1974 (Box 4A, Folder 4)
  - Boston Labor Committee to Combat Intolerance: Poster Campaign, 1948-1950 (Box 4A, Folder 5)
  - Boston Labor Committee to Combat Intolerance: Finances, 1968-1969, 1971 (Box 4A, Folder 6)
  - Boston Labor Committee to Combat Intolerance: Hearing, 1970 (Box 4A, Folder 7)
  - Boston Labor Committee to Combat Intolerance: MIT Study, 1964-1967 (Box 4A, Folder 8)
  - Boston Labor Committee to Combat Intolerance: Newspaper Clippings, 1969 (Box 4A, Folder 9)
  - Boston Labor Committee to Combat Intolerance: Report, undated (1969?) (Box 4A, Folder 10)
  - Boston Labor Committee to Combat Intolerance: Report, 1973 (Box 4A, Folder 11)
  - Boston News Digest, 1976 (Box 4A, Folder 12)
  - Boston Public Library, 1951-1960 (Box 4A, Folder 13)
  - Boston Public Library: Communist Propaganda Literature, 1952 (Box 4A, Folder 14)